<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Space Weather on Jeyaprakash's Portfolio</title><link>https://turbotrail.github.io/my-portfolio/tags/space-weather/</link><description>Recent content in Space Weather on Jeyaprakash's Portfolio</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://turbotrail.github.io/my-portfolio/tags/space-weather/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Have You Factored in Space Weather? ⚡🛰️</title><link>https://turbotrail.github.io/my-portfolio/posts/factored-in-space-weather-featured/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://turbotrail.github.io/my-portfolio/posts/factored-in-space-weather-featured/</guid><description>&lt;p>We often design for &lt;strong>heat&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>vibration&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>EMI&lt;/strong>, or &lt;strong>power surges&lt;/strong> — but what about &lt;strong>geomagnetic storms&lt;/strong>?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A &lt;strong>geomagnetic storm&lt;/strong> is a large-scale disturbance of Earth’s magnetic field, triggered by solar flares or coronal mass ejections (CMEs). When high-energy charged particles from the Sun hit our magnetosphere, they can induce powerful currents and electromagnetic effects.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="-why-this-matters-to-us-in-tech">🎯 Why this matters to us in tech:&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>🔹 &lt;strong>Satellite Systems&lt;/strong>: GPS, communications, and observation satellites face single-event upsets and orbital drag issues&lt;/li>
&lt;li>🔹 &lt;strong>Power Grids&lt;/strong>: Geomagnetically induced currents (GICs) can stress transformers and cause major blackouts&lt;/li>
&lt;li>🔹 &lt;strong>Aviation &amp;amp; Navigation&lt;/strong>: Polar flight routes and GNSS accuracy can be heavily impacted&lt;/li>
&lt;li>🔹 &lt;strong>Pipelines &amp;amp; Subsea Cables&lt;/strong>: Even underground infrastructure can suffer corrosion and current imbalance&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>As we move deeper into IoT, space systems, AI navigation, and satellite constellations, &lt;strong>space weather resilience&lt;/strong> becomes mission-critical.&lt;br>
The systems we build won’t just need to be fault-tolerant — they’ll need to be &lt;em>space-aware&lt;/em>. ☀️&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>